George Crabbe Collection
George Crabbe Collection
1883
Crabbe, George, fl. 1858-1883.
43 items (SC)
Papers of the Clergyman, Rector of Merton, Norfolk, close friend of Edward FitzGerald and executor, with Edmund Kerrich and Ernest G. Doughty, of the FitzGerald Estate. Correspondence, all of which is in connection with Edward FitzGerald's death while visiting the home of Crabbe. Includes sympathy letters from FitzGerald's friends and family as well as letters and documents concerning FitzGerald's will and the disposition of his property.
149372
Biographical History
George Crabbe (?-1884) was an English clergyman who served in Norfolk, as well as a friend of Edward FitzGerald.
Edward FitzGerald was born Edward Purcell on March 31, 1809 near Woodbridge in Suffolk. An English writer, FitzGerald is best known for his English translation of The Rubáiyát of Omar Khayyám.
George Crabbe was the grandson of the poet George Crabbe. Crabbe, the Rector of Merton, was a long-time friend of FitzGerald, and of Edmund Kerrich and Ernest G. Doughty, the executors of the FitzGerald estate. FitzGerald died in his sleep during his annual visit to Merton on June 14, 1883.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George Crabbe Collection consists of 43 items, all of which relate to the death, will, and disposition of property and personal effects of British author and translator Edward FitzGerald. Several letters in the collection offer expressions of sympathy to Crabbe from FitzGerald's friends and relatives (William E. Crowfoot, William Donne, Robert H. Groome, Annie Kerrich, Jane Wilkinson). Most of the other letters include discussions about the provisions of the will, arrangements for the evaluation of FitzGerald's art and book collections, and the disposition of his personal effects. E. G. Doughty writes ( 11 Aug 1883 ):
I think, no doubt, that the 'things' generally will go better sold here where FitzGerald's taste was known than afar off - so many wd. like a memento of him.
In addition to the 34 incoming letters is a copy of an Edward Fitzgerald letter ( Apr 1883 ) to his niece Frances Kerrich, in which he earmarks money to be set aside for herself and her sister Elizabeth, with provision for
...continuing certain little pensions and payments which I have made during my life in this neighbourhood, and which you can continue better than anyone else, inasmuch as you know some of the People, and well know the Howes here, who can tell you about all. Through them also you can pay what is to be paid to the several persons in question; whether half yearly, monthly, or weekly, as seems best for them and most convenient to you.
There are also two outgoing draft letters by George Crabbe.
Miscellany consists of six undated documents relating to the FitzGerald Estate.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into 2 series: correspondence and miscellany. Correspondence is separated into incoming and outgoing correspondence, with each subseries being arranged chronologically. There is an index to the correspondence located at the end of the finding aid.
Related Material
The 's rare book collection houses nearly 300 editions of The Rubáiyát of Omar Khayyám, including copies of FitzGerald's original translation. Please search for a complete listing.
In addition, the Alfred Terhune Collection relating to Edward FitzGerald contains material related to FitzGerald as does Robert Bernard Martin's manuscript of With Friends Possessed: a Life of Edward FitzGerald, a biographical study published in 1985.
Subject and Genre Headings
Cowell, Edward B. (Edward Byles), 1826-1903.; Crabbe, George, fl. 1858-1883 -- Archives.; Doughty, Ernest G.; FitzGerald, Edward, 1809-1883.; Groome, Francis Hindes, 1810-1889.; Kerrich, Edmund.; Kerrich, Frances.; Sotheby, Wilkinson & Hodge.; Clergy, Great Britain.; English literature, 19th century.; Executors and administrators, Great Britain.; Correspondence.; Clergy.; Executors and administrators.; Church and clergy; Literature -- British
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - Apr 1883, copy of letter by Edward FitzGerald to his niece, Frances Kerrich (Sc 95)
    - Jun 1883, 12 incoming letters, 2 folders (Sc 95)
    - Jul 1883, 8 incoming letters (Sc 95)
    - Aug 1883, 3 incoming letters (Sc 95)
    - Sep 1883, 2 incoming letters (Sc 95)
    - Oct 1883, 2 incoming letters (Sc 95)
    - Nov 1883, 5 incoming letters (Sc 95)
    - Dec 1883, undated, 2 incoming letters (Sc 95)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - Draft letters, undated; by George Crabbe; 2 outgoing letters (Sc 94)
- Miscellany
  - Documents relating to the Edward FitzGerald Estate, 6 items, 2 folders (Sc 95)
Index to Correspondence
Arnott, William 20 Aug 1883
Brooke, Francis Capper 12 Jul 1883
Cowell, Edward Byles 20 Jun 1883 23 Jun 1883
Crowfoot, William E. 15 Jun 1883
Donne, William 15 Jun 1883
Doughty, Ernest G. 27 Jul 1883 30 Jul 1883 11 Aug 1993 21 Nov 1883 5 Dec 1883 undated
Groome, Robert Hindes 15 Jun 1883 16 Jun 1883 21 Jun 1883
Jones, Richard 12 Jul 1883 17 July 1883
Kerrich, Annie 15 Jun 1883
Kerrich, Edmund 16 Jun 1883 27 Jun 1883, 10 Jul 1883 21 Jul 1883, 30 Jul 1883 11 Aug 1883
Kerrich, Frances 22 Jun 1883 14 Nov 1883, 16 Nov 1883 24 Nov 1883 27 Nov 1883
Lewis, S. S. (Samuel Savage?) 14 Sep 1883
Moor, George 11 Sep 1883 4 Oct 1883
Sotheby, Wilkinson & Hodge 9 Oct 1883
Wilkinson, Jane 29 Jun 1883